{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>The Vaganova method is used to teach this artform.</em> A company of these performers was renamed after a man whose death precipitated the Great Purge, Sergei Kirov. One of these pieces, performed for Richard Nixon on his 1972 visit to China, was <em>The Red Detachment of Women.</em> Its performers include defectors Rudolf Nureyev and Mikhail Baryshnikov. For 10 points, the Bolshoi performs what type of dance work typified by Tchaikovsky\u2019s <em>Swan Lake</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>ballet</u></b> dancing {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>In this year, England lost the Four Days\u2019 Battle against the Dutch.</em> An event in this year interrupted Christopher Wren's first efforts to restore St. Paul's Cathedral. This is the later year commemorated by John Dryden's poem <em>Annus Mirabilis</em>. During this year, Isaac Newton used a prism to produce the spectrum of visible light. In this year, Charles II returned to London from Salisbury at the end of the Great Plague. For 10 points, name this year in which the Great Fire of London occurred.", "answer": "<b><u>1666</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>In 1879, this man commissioned Solon Spencer Beman to design more than 1,300 buildings</em>. He previously took 4,000 acres near Lake Calumet to make a company town named for himself. This man's company was labeled \"un-American\" in 1894 and he was later forced to give up land to Chicago. Grover Cleveland stopped a strike against this man's company because it obstructed mail delivery. For 10 points, name this man who founded a namesake sleeping car company.", "answer": "George <b><u>Pullman</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man called Rube Waddell a \"hayseed\" while finishing throwing a perfect game</em>. Until Nolan Ryan, this man was the oldest person to throw a no-hitter. While playing for Boston, this man threw the first pitch in modern World Series history. His nickname referenced the fences he destroyed with his fastball, which looked like a storm had hit them. For 10 points, name this baseball player with a record 511 wins and the namesake for an award given to the best pitchers.", "answer": "Denton \u201cCy\u201d <b><u>Young</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>A fortification known as \u201cthe Circle\u201d was constructed during this campaign.</em> Lamachus died during this campaign, which included an incident in which several men were trampled to death in the Assinarus River. A general was recalled from this campaign after being implicated in the desecration of the Hermai. Gylippus led a defense of Syracuse during this campaign, which was proposed by Alcibiades (<b>pr. all-sib-EYE-uh-deez</b>). For 10 points, name this disastrous 415-413 BC Athenian campaign against a certain Mediterranean island.", "answer": "<b><u>Sicilian</u></b> (or Sicily) Expedition {I}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "<em>\"Vinegar Joe\" Stilwell's Marines were called to this island for a battle in May 1946</em>. Bernard Coy starved himself while on this island as part of a successful hostage taking plan. For about two years, starting in 1969, the United Indians of All Tribes occupied this island as a protest. Robert Stroud was the \"Birdman\" of this island, which is where \"Machine Gun\" Kelly ended up. For 10 points, name this island in San Francisco Bay used for years as a federal prison.", "answer": "<b><u>Alcatraz</u></b> Island [prompt on The <b><u>Rock</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>After this event, its leader was visited by journalist Edgar Snow.</em> At a meeting during this event, the 28 \"returned students\" and Otto Braun lost power. This event began after the success of the encirclement campaigns. The Zunyi Conference and the capture of Luding Bridge occurred during this event. This event ended after three armies were unified near the city of Yan'an in Shaanxi (<b>pr. SHON-shee</b>). For 10 points, name this lengthy retreat carried out by the Red Army under Mao.", "answer": "<b><u>Long March</u></b> [or <b><u>Changzheng</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>The name of these areas originated from a kind of tree encountered by veterans of the</em> <em>Canudos War.</em> The residents of one of these areas beat drums in the music video for Michael Jackson's \"They Don't Care About Us.\" An example of these areas known as \"City of God\" was made famous by the film of the same name. Another of these areas named Cantagalo is located near Copacabana. For 10 points, name these slums in Rio de Janeiro and other Brazilian cities.", "answer": "<b><u>favela</u></b>s (prompt on \u201cslums\u201d or equivalents)  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This man won election to the Senate after building a coalition against Philip Schuyler.</em> This man was arrested after being betrayed by James Wilkinson. After this man lost out in a tie broken by the House of Representatives in the election of 1800, the 12th Amendment was passed. This first vice-president of Thomas Jefferson was acquitted at his 1807 treason trial. For 10 points, name this man who killed Alexander Hamilton in a duel.", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Burr</u></b>, Jr.  {I}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>This man visited Azerbaijan and the Azov region on his \"Search for Odin.\"</em> This man's work <em>Hunt for Paradise</em> detailed his time at Fatu Hiva. This man posited that \"short eared\" and \"long eared\" people lived on Easter Island. This man used the boats <em>Ra</em> and <em>Ra II</em> to attempt to cross the Atlantic Ocean, and earlier arrived at the Tuamotu Islands in a handmade raft. For 10 points, name this Norwegian anthropologist who traveled across the Pacific Ocean on the <em>Kon-Tiki</em>.", "answer": "Thor <b><u>Heyerdahl</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>A depiction of the peace goddess Irene on this structure was replaced by a figure named</em> <em>Victoria.</em> A sculpted angel atop it holds a staff topped by a cross, on which an eagle perches. Napoleon's troops stole a statuary four-horse chariot which was later returned to the top of this structure. Carl Gotthard von Langhans designed it with inspiration from the Athenian Propylaea. It stands just south of the Reichstag. For 10 points, name this monumental, five-passageway gate in Berlin.", "answer": "<b><u>Brandenburg Gate</u></b> [or <b><u>Brandenburger Tor</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em>An investigation into this event by former FBI director William Webster faulted police chief</em> <em>Daryl Gates\u2019 response to it</em>. Mayor Tom Bradley declared a curfew during this event, which saw heavy damage in Koreatown. Truck driver Reginald Denny was smashed with a cinder block in this event. For 10 points, name this riot that occurred following the acquittal of police officers who were filmed beating an African-American motorist in a West Coast city.", "answer": "<b><u>1992 Los Angeles Riots</u></b> [or <b><u>Rodney King Riots</u></b>; or <b><u>South Central Riots</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The leader of this event was accompanied by Inare Kunati and refused to bow to Al-Nasir</em> <em>Muhammad at a meeting during it.</em> News of this event led to the depiction of its leader in the Catalan Atlas. During this event, the Andalusian al-Sahili was hired to build the Djinguereber Mosque. This event featured 500 herald carrying golden staffs and 80 camels carrying bags of gold. For 10 points, name this event in which a Mansa of the Mali empire visited Mecca.", "answer": "Mansa <b><u>Musa</u></b>'s <b><u>Hajj</u></b> [or anything indicating Mansa <b><u>Musa</u></b>'s <b><u>pilgrimage</u></b> to Mecca]  Mansa Musa's Djinguereber Mosque became part of the University of Timbuktu with the Sidi Yahya and what other university?  ANSWER: <b><u>Sankore</u></b> Madrasah  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>Another version of this project was negotiated with France two years later in the Mellon-Berenger agreement.</em> S. Parker Gilbert was appointed to oversee this project, which was created after the occupation of the Ruhr. Replaced by a proposal of Owen D. Young, this plan lay out a schedule that began with 1 billion gold marks the first year. For 10 points, name this 1924 plan for German reparations following World War I.", "answer": "<b><u>Dawes</u></b> Plan  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The final leader of these people lost at Tricamarum and Ad Decimum.</em> A leader of these people deposed his cousin, Hilderic, after Hilderic converted to Catholicism. Saint Augustine died during these people\u2019s siege of Hippo. These people, under the leadership of Genseric, stripped the roof tiles off a temple to Jupiter during their 455 sack of Rome. For 10 points, name these people who occupied Carthage and now lend their name to the destruction of property.", "answer": "<b><u>Vandal</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In a series of Israeli stories, this character twice defeats the Mau Mau and stops the Suez</em> <em>Canal blockade.</em> Hal Foster's first syndicated comic strip featured this character. Johnny Sheffield played this character's adopted son, and Maureen O'Sullivan played his wife, in the 1932 film in which this character's \"victory cry of the bull ape\" first was heard. For 10 points, a series of Edgar Rice Burroughs novels depicted what child of English nobility raised by apes?", "answer": "<b><u>Tarzan</u></b> [or John <b><u>Clayton</u></b>; or Viscount <b><u>Greystoke</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This event was investigated by the Kemeny Commission</em>. Governor Dick Thornburgh issued an evacuation order for children and pregnant women during it. This event was in part the result of the mistaken closing of the Unit 2 reactor valve, leading to a loss of coolant from the reactor core. For 10 points, identify this 1979 nuclear meltdown incident that took place at the namesake Pennsylvania power station.", "answer": "<b><u>Three Mile Island</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man\u2019s son Oskar was part of his group of advisors, the Carmarilla.</em> This man won one election after the BVP stopped supporting Wilhelm Marx. This man took one position following the death of Friedrich Ebert, and he signed the Reichstag Fire Decree<em>.</em> With Ludendorff, this man led the \u201csilent dictatorship\u201d in the latter years of World War I. For 10 points, name this German military commander who, as president of the Weimar Republic, appointed Hitler to be the chancellor of Germany.", "answer": "Paul von <b><u>Hindenburg</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man was the campaign manager for Gerald Ford\u2019s 1976 presidential campaign</em>. This man was the ranking republican on the House select committee investigating Iran-Contra. He served six terms as a congressman from Wyoming, and he coordinated the First Gulf War as secretary of defense for George H.W. Bush. This man was involved in a hunting accident with Harry Whittington while serving in his highest post. For 10 points, name this man who served as vice president under George W. Bush.", "answer": "Richard \u201cDick\u201d <b><u>Cheney</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This battle is commemorated by a large statue at Mamayev Kurgan.</em> Pavlov\u2019s House held for sixty days during this battle. A general in this battle was promoted to field marshal in an attempt to force him to continue fighting. This battle ended with General Paulus' surrender after a successful encirclement by General Zhukov's forces. In this battle, a counteroffensive was launched by the Soviets under Operation Uranus. For 10 points, name this turning point of World War II, fought over a city on the Volga River.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Stalingrad</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This person set the record for most vetoes in one term and also vetoed the Texas Seed Bill</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>He was hurt by the Murchison letter in one election. In another election, this former Mayor</u></b> <b><u>of (+)</u>Buffalo was taunted due to his affair with Maria Halpin with the slogan \u201cMa, (*) </b>Ma where\u2019s my Pa?\" He emerged victorious in that election after the Mugwumps defected from the writer of the Mulligan letters, the \u201cContinental Liar from the State of Maine\u201d named James G. Blaine. For 10 points, name this only president to serve two non-consecutive terms.", "answer": "Grover <b><u>Cleveland</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In a novel by this author set during Stalin's last years, people such as Lev Rubin and Gleb</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Nerzhin work on a telephone project as zeks.</u> </b></em><b><u>This author described the lives of several</u></b> <b><u>analysts in a Sharashka in one novel. This author's works of fiction include a novella in</u></b> <b><u>which the daily lives of people such as the privileged (+)</u> Caesar are seen by the protagonist (*)</b> Shukhov. For 10 points, name this Soviet author of<em> The First Circle,One Day in the Life of</em> <em>Ivan Denisovich,</em> and <em>The Gulag Archipelago</em>.", "answer": "Aleksandr <b><u>Solzhenitsyn</u> </b> {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The first leader of this organization, which was supported by the Vandenberg Resolution,</u></b></em> <em><b><u>was Lord Ismay.</u></b></em><b><u> It conducted yearly Able Archer readiness exercises. Members of this</u></b> <b><u>organization were asked to leave France by Charles (+)</u>De Gaulle. Article 5 of the treaty creating this entity was first invoked after the 9/11 attacks when this organization led the ISAF invasion of (*)</b> Afghanistan. For 10 points, name this organization based in Brussels which was opposed to the Warsaw Pact during the Cold War, a mutual defense organization led by the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>NATO</u></b> [or <b><u>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</u></b>; <b><u>North Atlantic Alliance</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man eloped with the already-married Anita de Jesus Ribeiro aboard his ship</u> </b></em><b><u>Rio</u></b> <b><u>Pardo</u></b><em><b><u> and fought alongside her thereafter.</u></b></em><b><u> This victor of the Battle of Sant'Antonio led the</u></b> <b><u>navy of a failed independence attempt of the Republic of (+)</u> Rio Grande do Sul before a conflict against Juan Manuelde Rosas. His troops adopted uniforms intended for a (*) </b>slaughterhouse before being tasked with the defense of Montevideo. For 10 points, name this man who fought against Argentina for Uruguay in the 1840s, a \"Hero of Two Worlds\" who later helped unite his native Italy by commanding the Red Shirts.", "answer": "Giuseppe <b><u>Garibaldi</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man foiled a plot against his society when letters sent to the Allobroges were</u></b></em> <em><b><u>intercepted.</u></b></em><b><u> This man was the prosecutor during the trial of a man who crossdressed at a</u></b> <b><u>Bona Dea festival. The</u> </b><em><b><u>Leges Clodiae</u> </b></em><b><u>were passed by a Tribune of the Plebs to target this (+)</u> politician. Publius Clodius Pulcher, who frequently attacked this politician, was murdered by men loyal to this man's friend (*)</b> Milo. This man spoke out in four orations against a conspiracy masterminded by the disgruntled Catiline. For 10 points, name this Roman orator who attacked Mark Antony in his <em>Philippics</em>.", "answer": "Marcus Tullius <b><u>Cicero</u></b> [or <b><u>Tully</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This scholar's distinction between \"instrumental rationality\" and \"value rationality\" led</u></b></em> <em><b><u>him to argue that academic research should be \"value-free.\"</u> </b></em><b><u>Talcott Parsons translated an</u></b> <b><u>introduction by this man which noted a \"line of development having universal significance</u></b> <b><u>and value\" \"in (+)</u> Western civilization, and Western civilization only.\" This man, who used the German word </b><em><b>Beruf</b></em><b> to describe science and politics as examples of secular calling, or (*) </b>\"vocation,\" argued that Dutch concern about worldly indicators of elect status boosted the Western European economy. For 10 points, name this sociologist who wrote <em>The Protestant</em> <em>Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism</em>.", "answer": "Max <b><u>Weber</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A copper workshop at this site was rediscovered in 1998, decades after their study by</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Gregory Perino.</u></b></em><b><u> It's not in Britain, but this site contains an arrangement of wooden poles</u></b> <b><u>used to mark the sun's movements termed (+)</u>Woodhenge. Depictions of a winged figure were found on the Birdman Tablets found at this site. A supposedly important individual was found buried here on top of a platform made of thousands of (*)</b> beads; that corpse was found in this site's Mound 72. The largest of the mounds at this location is Monks Mound. For 10 points, what site in southern Illinois was the greatest city in the Mississippian culture?", "answer": "<b><u>Cahokia</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A religious sect founded in this country, the Bogomils, believed that the world was created</u></b></em> <em><b><u>by the Devil.</u></b></em><b><u> This country is where Janos (</u></b><u>pr. YAH-noash</u><b><u>) Hunyadi's \"Long Campaign\"</u></b> <b><u>was defeated at the Battle of Varna. William Gladstone highlighted this country's</u></b> <b><u>namesake (+)</u>\"Horrors,\" which occurred as a result of the April Uprising. This country comprises much of the Ottoman territory ceded through the Treaty of (*)</b> San Stefano. This country's leader Todor Zhivkov was the longest-serving ruler in the Eastern Bloc. For 10 points, name this Balkan country ruled from Sofia.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Bulgaria</u></b> [or Republika <b><u>Balgarija</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This region's existence was first discovered by Charles Fabry and Henri Buisson.</u></b></em><b><u> Using a</u></b> <b><u>spectrophotometer he invented, G.M.B. Dobson first developed a method of studying this</u></b> <b><u>region. The Montreal Protocol was signed to stop a problem within (+)</u>this region. A large gap in this area opened in the 1980's above (*) </b>Antarctica, whosecause was determined to be CFCs and aerosols. For 10 points, name this layer in the stratosphere that forms protection from UV radiation, made up of an allotrope of oxygen.", "answer": "<b><u>ozone</u></b> layer [prompt on <b><u>stratosphere</u></b> until mentioned]  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>One holder of this position was embroiled in a scandal after he and his wife Leah were</u></b></em> <em><b><u>discovered to still have a joint dollar account in Washington DC during his term.</u></b></em><b><u> One holder</u></b> <b><u>of this position worked as a schoolteacher in Milwaukee and names the main library at (+)</u> the University of Wisconsin-Madison. One holder of this position authorized Operation Wrath of God in retaliation for the (*)</b> Munich Massacre. Another holder of this position was assassinated by Yigal Amir after signing the Oslo Accords. For 10 points, name this position whose holders have included Golda Meir and Yitzhak Rabin.", "answer": "<b><u>Prime Minister of Israel</u></b> [prompt on just \u201cPrime Minister\u201d do NOT accept \u201cPresident of Israel\u201d]  {I}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A work of political theory written in one of these places criticizes \"Taylorism\" and</u></b></em> <em><b><u>\"Fordism\".</u> </b></em><b><u>18</u>th<u> century etchings of imaginary places of this type by Piranesi were often</u></b> <b><u>purchased by students on the Grand Tour. Antonio (+)</u>Gramsci's Marxist notebooks were written while he was in an institution of this type during (*)</b> Mussolini's reign. Amanda Knox was put in one of these places after a murder she was later acquitted of while on study abroad in Italy. For 10 points, name these institutions affected by overcrowding in Italy today due to an overabundance of convicts.", "answer": "<b><u>prison</u></b>s [or <b><u>jail</u></b>s; or <b><u>penitentiaries</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}], "bonuses": []}